Dr.Tal Ben-Shahar: Hi.Good afternoon.Good morning.
大家好 下午好 早上好
Today we are going to continue talking about love.
今天我们继续谈论爱情
But before,if there is a Nadia in this room,
讲之前先说一下 一位叫Nadia的同学
and you left a key chain in class.
你的钥匙链落在这教室了
We have it here.
就在我这里
So please come and see me afterwards.
课后请来我这里取
So let's talk about love.
那我们来讲讲爱情吧
Last time,we left off with more questions than answers.
上节课我们留下的问题多过答案
The question was- difficult question was
问题是…很难的问题
"how can we sustain love?
"我们怎样维持爱情
How can we sustain passion beyond the honeymoon phase?"
怎样在热恋期后维持激情"
Because even if we did have our Brad Pitt or Halle Berry,
因为即便我们觅得自己的布拉德皮特
that does not guarantee lasting passion.
或海利贝瑞 也不能确保激情长存
In fact,what we know that does guarantee over time
其实真正能确定的是
is a waning of the physiological excitement that
我们和那个人历经的生理上的兴奋
we experience when we are with that person.
会慢慢淡去
And that in part explains some of the statistics,
这在一定程度上解释了几个数据
such as 2/3 of marriages end up in divorce,
三分之二的婚姻以离婚告终
such as even those who do stay together
那些即便以后没有分开
after a while it's out of convenience,
也是出于省事
out of a sense of duty and not always,
出于责任
or more often than not
而不是因为
does not have the same sense of togetherness of passion
曾经在一起时的那种激情
that existed at the beginning of the relationship
那种在恋情一开始时存在的
with all the good intentions and the hope of the life-long
带着想要与之共度终生的
committed relationship- marriage or otherwise.
彼此承诺与对方长相厮守的美好夙愿
And then we asked "what positive psychology can do for us?"
若问"幸福心理学能为我们做什么?"
We asked the additional question to the normal question
这是对另一个问题的提问
that has been asked for many years,
另一个被问了很多年的问题
which is "why do so many relationships fail?"
"为什么这么多恋情失败的例子"?
It's an important question.It's necessary.
这问题很重要 很有必要问
It's very far from being sufficient.
这个问题涵盖面远远不够
And it leads to the same errors,
但这个问题犯了一个错误
to the same shortcomings that asking only the negative question
它有一个缺点 只问了消极的问题
leads to when we are studying at risk youth,
当我们研究问题少年
when we are studying time management and stress.
时间管理与压力时 也犯了这样的错误
Because when we only ask one of the questions,
因为当我们只问了消极的问题时
what we are missing are the children on the bus,
我们就会看不到巴士上的孩子
metaphorically speaking.
这是一个比喻
What we are missing are the colors in the reality in front us,
我们就会看不到眼前真实的颜色
if the only question we focus on is
如果我们仅关注一个问题
"how many geometric shapes are there?" Questions create reality.
"一共有多少几何形状?" 问题决定现实
And very often,if we don't certain question,
很多时候 如果我们不问某个问题
certain answers are obscure and disappear.
某些答案就不会出来
So we ask this question
所以我们来问这个问题
and we ask not just about "what makes relationships work",
不仅问"怎样让恋情维系下去"
but "what makes relationships thrive?"
还要问"怎样让恋情美好下去"
And psychologists such as David Schnarch and John Gottman
如David Schnarch和John Gottman两位心理学家
in their extraordinary books,
在他们写的大作中
extraordinary research talk about some of these characteristics.
在他们的研究中 谈过这些方法特征
So let's get into them.
让我们来了解一下
The first one is about working hard.
第一个方法是努力
This is the world's best kept secret.It's the secret of success.
努力是世界上守得最好的秘诀 是成功的秘诀
It's the secret of personal success,of successful relationships.
是个人成功的秘诀 是感情成功的秘诀
There are no short cuts-
成功没有捷径
if we want a relationship to thrive,to succeed,
若想让一段恋情一直美好
we need to put a lot of work in it.
我们就得为之努力
Now that seems self-evident,obvious common sense.
这看起来似乎是不言而明的普遍常识
But so often in this class we have seen
但在这个班上 我们经常体会到
what Voltaire has remarked,"common sense is not that common."
正如伏尔泰所说"常识没那么寻常"
Now why is common sense not that common?
为什么要用常识来维持一段恋情时
When it applies to working hard in a relationship.
却发现这样的常识不是人人都有?
The reason is because
这是因为
many people have wrong expectations of the relationship
很多人对恋情有着错误的期望
or of what it means to have happy relationships specifically.
或者确切的说 对美好的恋情有着错误的期望
Most people believe that the most important part
大多数人认为拥有一段美好的
of enjoying a happy life-long committed relationship
至死不渝的恋情的关键在于
is finding the right partner.
寻找到真命天子
And that's certainly important,
这确实重要
but it is a mistake to focus on finding.
但是错在了将重点放在寻找上面
People have- if we draw an analogy to Carol Dweck's research
我们也套用一下Carol Dweck研究中的
on fixed versus malleable mindset-
固定心态和可塑心态的对比
people have a finding mindset that hurts the relationship.
人们有一种会破坏恋情的寻找心态
Let me explain.
我来为大家解释一下
So going back- we did this before spring break.
先回到春假前我们讲过的知识
What Carol Dweck showed was
Carol Dweck证明了
when we praise people for their intelligence-
当人们获得游戏测试成绩后
"oh you are so smart"-
我们赞赏他们"你真聪明"
after doing well on the test,they enter the fixed mindset.
这时他们就有了固定心态
Versus if we praise them for "oh you've worked so hard".
相反 如果我们赞他们"你真努力"
They have a malleable mindset.And that has consequences.
他们就有了可塑心态 这两种心态都会产生影响
Because the fixed mindset-
因为固定心态
the intelligence- "you are so smart" doesn't help them much.
即赞赏"你真聪明"帮不上什么
And then when they go to the next puzzle,
却在他们进入下一轮测试时
next task which is difficult,that threatens their schema-
当测试变难 威胁到对自己的自我定位
"oh if I don't get it,if I don't succeed,
"若做不出来
it means I'm no longer smart." And they give up more easily.
便说明我不聪明了" 这时他们便更容易放弃
They are more threatened by failure.
他们更易被失败威胁到
And they don't enjoy the process.
他们也无法享受过程
They become perfectionists,
他们变成了完美主义者
or more likely to become perfectionists.
或者说更倾向于变成完美主义者
OK,so this is the fixed mindset.
这就是固定心态
You are so smart.You are so intelligent.
你真聪明 你的智商真高
The malleable mindset- "oh you work so hard".
而可塑心态 "你真努力"
Oh I can work with that.
我会努力做的
So even if I don't succeed,don't do well,
即便我没成功 没做好
I can still learn and I do learn to enjoy the process more.
我也照样能学习 能够更享受过程
So that's the malleable mindset.
这就是可塑心态
Now let's draw an analogy to what we've just discussed here.
现在将这个理论运用到恋情上来
If I believe that the most important thing
如果我认为拥有一段至死不渝的
about enjoying life-long,committed,
幸福的恋情的最关键所在
happy relationship is finding the right partner,
寻找到真命天子
I enter what I call- again by analogy,the finding mindset,
这里的寻找心态就相当于
which will be an equivalent to Dweck's fixed mindset.
Dweck提出的固定心态
And then let's say I have this mindset.
假设我现在就有这种寻找心态
This is the most important thing.
认为这是最重要的事
And then we go through a rough patch in our relationship.
此时若我们的恋情经历一段艰难岁月
Then what happens? Then I begin to think "wait a minute.
接下来会怎样呢?我会开始思索
Something's wrong here.I must have not found the right partner.
"不对 我肯定是还未找到真命天子
I must have made a mistake- an error of judgment."
我肯定弄错了 找错了对象"
And that very often leads to a worsening of the situation.
这种心态常会让情况恶化
And it can,doesn't always,but can lead to a downward spiral.
可能会导致恶性循环
This is the finding mindset.
这就是寻找心态
Because it's fixed I found my knight in shining armor.
因为这种心态是固定的 我找到了白马王子
I found my dream woman.I found my Brad Pitt,my Halle Berry.
我找到了自己的女神 我的皮特我的贝瑞
And you know that problem is that reality inevitably hits.
问题是现实总是残酷的
We can't run away from it.
我们无法脱离现实
And reality dictates that there are no perfect relationships.
现实证明完美的恋情根本不存在
Remember that Leo Buscaglia's quote about,
记住Leo Buscaglia曾说过
"perfect love is rare indeed."
"完美的爱情少之又少"
No it's not rare.It doesn't exist.
不 不是少 而是没有
And when we realize that-
当我们意识到
if we have the finding mindset,the fixed mindset,
若我们有了寻找心态 这种固定心态
it threatens our schema.
它会威胁到我们的自我认定
There is inconsistency and then we begin to think
一有矛盾发生我们就开始琢磨
"well I probably did not find the right person."
"估计我还没找到真命天子"
In contrast,if we have the cultivating mindset,that's malleable
若我们反过来抱着培养心态 这种心态是可塑的
That's related to the effort part- "OK.
它与我们的努力相关 "好的
So we are going through a hardship.
我们的感情碰到了困难
We are going through difficulty.
我们在经历困境
But it's OK.Because we are working on it.
但不怕 因为我们在努力改善
We are working to resolve it."
我们在努力解决问题"
It's like the students who were praised for their effort- "OK.
这就像那些被赞扬努力的学生 "好的
So I'm not solving this puzzle now.
虽然我现在解决不了问题
But so what? I'm putting in a lot of effort.
但又怎样呢?我在努力
I'm trying; I'm even enjoying the process."
我在尝试 我甚至在享受这过程"
Look at the direct parallel here between Dweck's work
看这类比多么相似 Dweck研究的心态
on mindset and our mindset when it comes to relationships.
和我们用在恋情上的心态
So important- it makes such big difference.
如此之重要 两种心态 结果相差甚远
And very often we can switch it-
很多时候我们是可以转变这心态的
not immediately,relatively promptly.
不是马上可以变 但也不用太多时间
Remember Carol Dweck was able to change mindset of people
要知道Carol Dweck能靠一个
in a single experiment,in a few hours.
几小时的实验就将人们的心态转变
And we can do the same in our relationship
我们也能在对待恋情上转变心态
if we truly accept and internalize the fact
只要我们真正接受并内化一个事实
that relationships or finding the right partner,
那就是在一段恋情中 找到真命天子
a good partner is of course important.
找到合适的人 当然重要
It is much more important to then cultivate that relationship.
但培养一段感情更重要
We'll get to that in a minute.
这个一会再讲
But the question then arises:
但是问题接踵而来
so why do people have the finding mindset?
为什么人们会有寻找心态呢?
Why do people have or not have the cultivating mindset?
如果培养心态更健康
If it is healthier.
为什么人们没有培养心态呢?
One of the main reasons are the movies.Now movies are wonderful.
主要原因之一在于电影 现在的电影很精彩
They are terrific.They show us what is possible.
电影很棒 向我们展现一切皆有可能
Aristotle once said about art that it's -or about fiction-
亚里士多德曾对小说发表如下看法
that it's more important than history,
小说远重于历史
because history depicts things as they are,
因为历史只是白描
whereas fiction depicts things as they can and ought to be.
而小说却将一切描述到了极致
So it's a wonderful thing;
所以说电影是很美好的
it shows us some model of what's possible,
它让我们看到了可能性
especially the romantic movies.
尤其是浪漫的电影
I don't mean romantic in terms of love,
这里的浪漫不是指爱情上的浪漫
romantic in the 18th,19th centuries sense of romantic,
是指18 19世纪的浪漫主义
showing us how things can work,how things can become,
向我们展示事物可以有多美好
the potential,human nature relationships of our world.
潜在的人性 我们与世界的关系
So it's a wonderful thing.
这是件很美妙的事
But one thing that movies don't do well is that
但是电影有一点没做好
they focus on the finding of the right partner,
电影聚焦于找到真命天子
and hence very often entrench,reinforce the finding mindset.
于是这就巩固加强了寻找心态
Because most of the movies,
因为大多数电影
love stories look like this: there are struggles;
爱情故事总是这样的 有挣扎
there are fights; there are disagreements;
有争吵 有意见相左
there are challenges on the way.
途中挑战不断
And then at the end,
到最后
Mr and Mrs Smith get together and they live happily ever after.
Smith夫妇走到了一起 从此幸福生活
The screen drops and they walk into the sunset.
荧幕落下 他们走向夕阳
You know what problem is with that picture?
你们知道这画面有什么问题吗?
The problem is that movies end where love begins.
问题就在于 爱情才刚开始 电影就结束了
It is after the screen drops that the actual work starts.
荧幕落下后才要开始真正的努力
It is easy to have a good relationship at the beginning,
在刚开始时 要恋情顺利是很容易的
the honey moon phase
蜜月期
or you know through the first year or two usually.
或者说一开始的一两年
But then what happens after a while
但是这之后
when the initial physical,physiological instinct wanes?
当最初的肉体上 生理本能淡去
What happens when we start to recognize and understand
当我们开始意识到
and realize and see that- well this partner is not perfect.
我们的伴侣并不完美时会怎样?
What happens then? Well,that's when true love begins.
会怎样?这就是爱情开始的时候了
And that's where true love is cultivated and formed.
这也是真爱得以培养并形成之际
Now I'm not belittling the importance of finding a partner,
我并不是贬损寻找
the right partner,the right person for us.
真命天子的重要性
It is of course important.
这当然重要
And often it takes kissing many frogs before we find our prince.
通常找到王子前要亲无数只青蛙
But the more important part of a thriving long term relationship
但是对于一份美好而持久的恋情
is the cultivation.
培养更重要
This is where the effort starts.
这才是努力开始的地方
It's after the sunset; the difficulties and hardships rise.
在日落之后 困难与险阻浮现
Now connect it to this,to the mindset is the notion
与寻找心态紧紧相连的
that there is only one right person for us.
是真命天子只有一个这样的观念
And all I need to do,all I need to dedicate all my effort
我所需要做的就是
and time to is find that right person.
穷尽一生找到那个真命天子
And if I have to go all the way to Yale
如果得去耶鲁大学找
I'll go there to find that person.
我也会愿意去
A modern version of a Shakespeare in tragedy perhaps.
就像是莎翁悲剧的现代版
Whatever I need to do I will do it-
不论需要做什么 我都愿意做
just to find that one right person-
只要能找到真命天子
even if I'm in Boston,they are in Seattle.
即便我在波士顿 他们在西雅图
I will find that right person.
我总会找到真命天子
I don't believe that.It's simply not true.
我不信这套 不现实
It's not the matter of faith.
这不是信念的问题
I mean we know many people
我的意思是 很多人
who thought they found the right person,
觉得找到了真命天子
maybe did find the right person,
也许确实是找到了
and then either for tragic reasons
却因为不幸的原因
or for good reasons they were no longer together.
或是为了正确的原因 没能继续下去
And they found more love.
他们之后反而找到更多爱情
There are 6 billion people in the world.
这世界上有60亿人口
There's more than one right person.
真命天子绝非仅一个
So what makes relationship unique?
那么是什么让恋情独特的呢?
It's not finding that one right person.
不是找到真命天子
Once again it's cultivating that one chosen relationship.
而是与你选择的恋人培养恋情
It's by virtue of working together,of being together,
通过共同的努力 共同在一起
of spending time together,of dedicating one another.
共同度过 彼此奉献
That's how we create the one chosen relationship,
这是创造一段恋情的方式
one special relationship.
一段独特的恋情
That's how two separate "I"s become a "we".
让两个"我"变成一个"我们"
And again to do that,it doesn't happen over night.
再次重申 这不能在一夜间完成
It doesn't even happen in a year or two.It takes time.
甚至不能在一两年里完成 需要时间
In fact,it doesn't happen; it is happening.It's a process.
事实上感情没有完成一说 这是一个过程
It's not about success in a relationship;
它无关恋情的成功
it's about succeeding in a relationship.
而是恋情的延续
We cultivated relationship not just simply by putting on the ring
恋情的培养不仅靠交换戒指
or by giving the vows.
或是结婚誓言
It's by doing things together.
而更要靠共同参与
Why is that so important?
这为什么很重要呢?
Let me draw on some research from other areas of psychology.
我们讲一下心理学其他领域的研究
And this is something that I mentioned on a couple of occasions.
我在其他场合曾提过几次
Some of the most important work done by Muzafer Sherif
Muzafer Sherif在20世纪50年代
back in the 1950s,and until Muzafer Sherif came along.
完成的伟大研究之一 在Muzafer Sherif之前
As I mentioned before,the hypothesis that people had
我之前说过了 人们有这样一个假说
when it comes to resolving interpersonal conflicts
当要解决人际冲突
or inter-group conflicts,
或者群体间冲突时
the belief that people had was that
人们认为此时的解决方法就是
all you need to do is get the conflicting sides together.
让冲突双方聚在一起就行了
The dominant hypothesis was what's called "contact hypothesis".
这个主流假说被称为"接触假说"
Get the two conflicting sides in touch with one another
让冲突双方相接触
whether it's conflicting ethnic groups,
无论是族群冲突
whether it's conflicting individuals.
还是个人间冲突
Get them together and you will resolve the conflict.
让他们聚在一起 冲突就能解决
This was much of the work done by Gordon Allport
这一理论主要由Gordon Allport提出
in our department here back in the 1930s.
在20世纪30年代我们的心理学系
Muzafer Sherif comes along and shows that that's not the case.
Muzafer Sherif出现后 指出这不行
In fact,just bringing them together,
事实上 仅让冲突双方聚首
just the contact of the conflicting sides very often,more often
让冲突双方接触
than not intensifies the conflict rather than resolve it.
通常反而会激化矛盾 而非解决矛盾
And I gave this in a context of Arabic-Israelis conflict,
我讲这个时 用阿以冲突作为例子
where people just got together
那里的人们聚在一起
and hope that there will be peace in our time.
希望能实现两国间的和平交往
And instead we got more war in our time.Contact is not enough.
但反而挑起了更多的战争 仅接触是不够的
Not when it comes to bringing nations together;
不仅不适用于国家间冲突
not when it comes to bringing ethnic groups together;
不适用于族群间冲突
and not when it comes to bringing a couple together.
也不适用于夫妻间冲突
You see in a relationship,inevitably there are conflicts.
一段恋情中 发生冲突不可避免
Inevitably.There is no perfect relationship.
这世上没有完美的恋情
And if there were perfect relationship,
即便有了完美恋情
it would not be a conflict-free relationship,
也会有冲突的完美恋情
as we'll see shortly.
对此马上会为大家讲解到
So there are conflicts in our relationship-
我们的恋情会有冲突
whether it's during the first year
不是在第一年里出现
or whether it's after two or three years.
就是在两三年后出现
And serious conflicts- I'm not just saying about you know,
而至于重大冲突 这里不是指
conflict about "well you should put down the toilet seat"
类似于"你怎么不放下马桶盖"
or "keep it up".
"把马桶盖掀起来"的冲突
I mean serious conflicts.Well that could be serious I guess.
当然马桶盖冲突也会变得很严重
But other serious conflicts.
但我指的是其他重大冲突
And when there is a conflict,
当这样的重大冲突出现时
and all the couples are doing together,simply being together,
一段关系中的双方只是聚在一起
in touch with one another-
相互接触
that's not enough to resolve that conflict.
这不足以解决冲突
And very often it will start as a minor conflict
很多情况下 反而会由小冲突
and then get worse- spiral up,or rather spiral down over time.
转化为大冲突 冲突逐渐升级
So what does Sherif say and what do we know today?
Sherif对此有什么建议?我们研究出什么方法了?
That the important thing in resolving conflicts
解决冲突的要点之一
is having a super ordinate goal.
在于确立一个超然目标
When the two ethnic groups,when the two nations work together,
当两个民族或国家共同努力
and are inter-dependent-
彼此互助
whether it's in business,or in a relationship,
无论在公事上还是恋情上
it could be raising children- but doing the things together,
例如共同抚养孩子 只要共同努力
or belonging to the same political campaign,
不管属于同一个政治阵营
or opposite political campaigns- that's fine.
还是相对立的两个政治阵营 都可以
But working together,
只要共同努力
supporting one another and when you have the working together,
彼此支持对方 当你们共同努力
the doing together,
共同参与时
that's when you are most likely to resolve the conflicts.
才是你们可能解决冲突之时
And in fact these conflicts as we'll see shortly
我们很快就会看到这样的冲突
can make the relationship even stronger.
反而还能让恋情变得更加巩固
But the couple need mutually meaningful goals.
但情侣间需要共同的有意义的目标
And again,it could be having children together
再说一遍 可以是一起要个孩子
and raising the children together.
共同抚养
You know not just the "OK.We had the child.
不是"我们有个孩子
And then the mother or the father raise the kid-
由父亲或母亲抚养
more often the mother."
通常会是母亲"这样
And OK.So we did something together.No.
这样不算是共同努力了
The kid has to be to put in a very delicate and-
孩子必须处于一种微妙的位置
I'm sure appropriate terms- the kid has to be a joint venture.
用专业术语来说 孩子应是合资企业
Isn't it a lovely term to describe having kids?
用这个术语来比喻生孩子是不是很有爱?
As long as they don't bring any bad debt
只要他们不带来任何坏账
or you know there is a good return on investment.
对他们的投资会带来很好的回报
Yeah,just the right language there.
非常适合的经济学术语
Took me a while to think about it.
琢磨琢磨一下就往上套
So working together,bringing up the kids together,
共同做事 共同抚育孩子
or being on campaigns together,
或是共同参与竞选
or helping one another at work but doing things together.
或在工作上给对方帮助 但要共同为之
John Gottman: "In the strongest marriages,
John Gottman说过"最稳固的婚姻里
husband and wife share a deep sense of meaning.
丈夫与妻子彼此间深度融合
They don't just "get along"-
他们不只是一起生活
they also support each other's hopes and aspirations
他们还支持彼此的愿望与抱负
and build a sense of purpose into their lives together."
为他们的生活融入共同的目标"
That doesn't mean that they have to do everything together.
这不是说他们要什么都一起做
I mean it's OK
我的意思是
for one to have his or her own meaningful goals at work,
他或她可以在工作上有自己的目标
where they don't work together- that's perfectly fine.
而他们并不一起工作 这完全没问题
But in addition there have to be things that are done together.
但是必须要有他们共同做的事
In other words,what we need is an active kind of love.
换言之 我们需要的是主动的爱情
You know the first time I really understood
我第一次理解主动爱情的含义
the meaning the active love was through a story that Shahar
还是通过Shahar给我讲的一个故事
who's one of my best friends in Israel told me.
他是我在以色列最好的朋友之一
We were in the same class,
我们过去是同班同学
but he got married at a relatively young age.
不过他很早就结婚了
It was in his early 20s and had his first kid soon after.
他二十出头就结了婚 很快有了儿子
And he is very introspective,
他是一个非常善于自省
very honest,high levels of integrity.
很诚实很正直的人
And he told me at the beginning when he had Noam,
他告诉我 刚生儿子Noam时
when Noam came home from hospital with his wife,his mom,
当他的母亲与妻子带着Noam从医院回到家
Shahar didn't really feel love toward Noam.
Shahar并未感受到对Noam的爱
He was very cute and adorable.
儿子很可爱 很招人喜欢
But he didn't feel a strong sense of love that
但他对儿子没有自己想象中
he thought he should have felt.
那么深爱
Needless to say he felt enormously guilty about it.
更别提他对此有多愧疚了
That didn't last for long fortunately.
幸运的是这没有持续很久
Because as soon as Shahar started to taking care,
因为自从Shahar开始照顾儿子
started taking care of Noam which meant changing his diapers,
比如为他换尿布
which meant getting up in middle of the night and feeding him,
大半夜起来给他喂奶
which meant taking him for walks,which meant cleaning after him-
带他散步 给他擦洗身体
that's when the love was cultivated.
爱就这样培养出来了
That's when he started to feel a deep sense of fatherhood
平生第一次他感到了
for the first time.
父亲对儿子的爱
So it wasn't natural.
这感情不是自然而然便有的
For some people it is natural- for women more often,
对有些人是天生的 尤其是女性
but not always,more often than men.
但不是女生都是这样 总体来说高于男人
So we can rely on and wait for this natural thing to happen
我们可以等着这感觉自然发生
or we can actively engage in activities
也可以主动参与其中
that show and illustrate our love.
表达我们的爱
Remember self-perception theory?
还记得自我知觉理论吗?
We very often form theories and beliefs about ourselves
我们总是以自己的行为为基础
based on how we behave.
形成自我的理论及信条
So examples we used in the past:
我们过去曾讲过的例子
if I see myself going up to someone and ask them out,
如果我想象自己会去约会某人
even if they say no,I perceive myself as someone with confidence
即便她们说不 我也感到了自信
And my self-esteem will go up,regardless of the response.
无论对方答不答应 我的自尊都会上升
If I see myself trying out for plays,
若我想象自己能去演戏
I will perceive myself as someone courageous.
我会感到自己是有勇气的
If I perceive myself as...
如果我感到自己
If if I take care of myself,I'll see myself
如果我照顾自己 我会感到自己
as someone with self-esteem who cares about him or herself.
是自尊自爱 关心自己或关心她的人
So the same with children.
这对孩子也是一样的
If I see myself taking care of my child,
若我想象自己能照顾孩子
my conclusion in self-perception theory
根据自我知觉理论 我会得出
is "oh I must love that child".
"我一定很爱那孩子"的结论
And that love actually intensifies over time,
这爱会随着时间而加深
whether it's with children,whether it's with partners.
无论是对孩子还是对伴侣
We may experience the love automatically at the beginning;
爱情开始时也许是自发感受到的
it could be the love at the first sight.
也许是一见钟情
However,if we don't sustain the active love,
尽管如此 若我们不主动维持爱情
over time because of self-perception theory,
长此以往 由于自我知觉理论
over time that will go away.
那份最初的激情会淡去
Because I don't invest anything in a relationship,
因为我们没在恋情中有所投入
self-perception theory-
自我知觉理论会告诉我们
"oh it must not be that important for you."
"这恋情对我一定不怎么重要"
And then the love wanes- not to mention
爱情慢慢淡去 更不必提
all the physiological reasons why it wanes over time.
激情被时间冲刷掉的生理原因了
So if there isn't the active love,it cannot be sustained.
如果没有主动爱情 则恋情无以为继
How do we sustain love? How do we remain active?
我们怎样维持爱情?保持主动?
Realtionship rituals.You know we talked about the rituals.
恋情老规矩 我们谈过老规矩
I told you about the rituals that
我跟你们讲过我和我妻子的老规矩
my wife and I had usually- have,two days a week,
至少每周两次
meals with the whole family additional at least.
与全家共进晚餐
Once a week,usually it's three or four times a week.
一般每周会有三四次
But we have these rituals.
但我们确有这些老规矩
Because without rituals,in our modern world,
因为在现代社会 若没有这些老规矩
the important yet not urgent in the words of Steven Covey,
用Steven Covey的话说是 重要却非紧急
the important and yet not urgent activities will take a backseat.
重要却非紧急的活动就会被冷落
So yeah we know it's important to go on dates.
即便我们知道出去约会很重要
But it's not as urgent as phone call I just receive from work
但不如刚接到的工作来电紧急
and I have to wait or stay at work,whereas if there is a ritual,
所以我不得不放弃约会 留下来加班 然而若有老规矩
if we do it no matter what then it will sustain itself.
不管遇到什么事都坚持老规矩 感情就得以维持
The second way and extremely important way of sustaining love
第二种维持爱情重要的途径是
is making that shift
做出改变
from desire to be validated to the desire to be known.
从想要被认可 到想要被了解
This advice that I got from David Schnarch
这个建议来自David Schnarch
in his book "Passionate Marriage"-
出自他的书"充满激情的婚姻"
this single advice
就是这个简单的建议
has quite literally transformed my relationships,
真正地改变了我与人们的关系
whether it's my romantic relationship with my wife
包括我与妻子的恋情
or my relationship with my friends,
我与朋友的友情
family members as well as students.
与家人的亲情 甚至于师生情
And I mention this before,and I want to go more in depth here.
这点在以前提过 再讲深一点
Because it is so crucial for sustaining passion,
因为这对维持激情至关重要
for sustaining friendship,for sustaining happiness.
对于维持友情 维持快乐
Individual- intrapersonal as well as inter-personal happiness.
维持个人内心的 以及人与人间的快乐
So what does that mean?
这意味着什么呢?
What is being known rather than being validated mean?
什么叫被了解而非被认可呢?
First of all one thing that David Schnarch and others have shown
首先 David Schnarch及其他心理学家
is that if we want to sustain passion beyond the honeymoon phase,
表明了 如果我们想在蜜月期后 在一见钟情后
beyond the time when it's automatic,
仍然维持着激情
what we need to do is form deeper levels of intimacy.
我们就得形成深层次的亲密关系
And couples- again now we are studying couples
那些接受我们研究调查的伴侣
who have been together for 20,30,40 years
他们已共同生活了几十年
and still have a passionate relationship.
却依然有着充满激情的恋情
Couples who do that,the tip of the stem unfortunately,
很不幸 这样的伴侣少之又少
but couples who do that,
但确实存在
have cultivated and continue to cultivate-
他们的一生都在培养 并一直培养
not find- cultivate intimacy throughout their lives.
而非花一生时间寻找亲密关系
And how do you cultivate intimacy?
你们知道怎样培养亲密关系吗?
By getting to know one another more and more,
通过逐渐了解对方
more deeply,more meaningfully.
逐渐加深了解
By understanding one another,
通过理解对方
by getting to know one another as we know ourselves.
通过像了解自己一样了解对方
And that means that if we are up to be known by the other partner
这意味着 我们若决心让对方了解自己
that means we must open up.
我们就必须打开心扉
That means we must reveal.
我们必须吐露心声
That means we need to share of ourselves-
这意味着我们得彼此分享
not just the wonderful and the amazing and the terrific things
不只是那些在首次约会分享的
that we share on the first date.That too.
精彩美妙的事 当然也包括这些
But in addition,
但是除此以外
also the things that sometimes we are not that proud of.
还包括一些让我们不怎么自豪的事
Our weaknesses perhaps.
也许是我们的缺点
Some of the things that maybe we are ashamed of,
也许是我们耻于提及的
that we don't feel very comfortable...
让我们觉得不舒服
That no one knows about us.
不为人知的事情
Now that does not happen on the first date-
这些事不会在首次约会上讲出来
it shouldn't happened on the first date.
这也不该在首次约会讲
Very often it doesn't happen after 5 or 10  years.
很多情况下 甚至不会在五年十年内讲
It happens gradually over time as trust increases,
只有经过长年累月的信任加增
and reveal more and more...
逐渐坦露出来
Sometimes we reveal things about ourselves
有时我们坦露的是
that we didn't even know that existed;
自己都不知道的
that we repressed or suppressed over time.
被我们压抑了很久的事
But it takes time,
但这需要时间
which is why going back to David Schnarch's quote
这也是要回到David Schnarch关于
about cellulite and sexual potential,
脂肪团和性能力的言论上
that usually happens after age 10,20,30 years,
这通常发生在10年20年30年后
which is why at the age of 50 and 60,
这也是为什么到了五六十岁时
there is even better sexual potential
甚至会有比18 20 30岁时
than at the age of 18 or 20 or 30.
更强的性能力
Doesn't mean it can't be great at 18,20 and 30,
倒不是说18 20 30岁时不好
but it can be even greater.Why?
而是会比年轻时更好 为什么?
Because deeper levels of intimacy,deeper level of connectedness.
因为有了更深层的亲密联系
A lot of look forward to,
若我们理解了充满激情的关系的本质
if we understand what is the nature of passionate relationship.
这段关系就有很多东西值得我们期待
It cannot just rely on "well we came together;
这不能仅靠"我们在一起
I found my princess/prince charming and we'll live happily after"
我找到了梦中情人 我们会幸福一生"
No,it means also taking risks at times.
不是这样的 这有时是有风险的
It means revealing over time our deepest desires,
意味着除了坦露我们内心深处的需求
our deepest fantasies,
我们最深的幻想
our greatest strengths as well as our weaknesses,
我们最厉害的长处 还有我们的缺点
our insecurities and our passions.
我们的不安及痛苦
That is what it means to be revealed,to open up,to share.
要坦露 要敞开心扉 就要做到这些
What it means is that
这意味着
a healthy relationship is about expressing ourselves
一段健康的恋情 需要我们表达自己
rather than trying to constantly impress.
而非长期抑制自己
This is the difference between being known-
这就是被了解与被认可的区别
express versus being validated- let me impress her;
被了解是要表达自己
let me impress him; let me impress them.
被认可则是要取悦别人
The thing about this is that- yes,
这样做是有缺点
it is more risky to open up,to express ourselves.
敞开心扉表达自己风险更高
Because what if she doesn't like me?
因为若她不喜欢这样的我 怎么办?
What if he doesn't like what he finds out about me?
如果他深入了解我后 不喜欢我怎么办?
But you see when we express,
但是要知道当我们表达自己时
we are more likely to have a thriving relationship-
我们更可能收获一段美好的恋情
it's not guaranteed by any stretch of imagination.
但是没什么可以保证一定就有好恋情
It's not guaranteed.
这无法保证的
However if we just impress,we are guaranteed failure.
然而若我们一味抑制自己 失败是肯定的
Here is why.
原因如下
First of all,when we express,generally,over time,
首先 当我们逐渐敞开心扉
maybe not in the short term,but over time,
也许短时间内没有效果 但是
people will be more attracted to us,-
随着时间的流逝 人们会被我们吸引
specifically my partner will like me even more over time
特别是我的伴侣会逐渐更喜欢我
because of our deeper levels of intimacy,
因为我们有了深层次的亲密关系
even they sometimes find out things that
即便有时他们对于刚了解的
they don't necessarily like or adore or appreciate.
关于我们的事不是很喜欢或赞赏
Over time it's people who are genuine,
但久而久之 真诚的人
who will attract other people and-
会吸引到其他人
by the way this applies in the realm of C
而且 这种方法也适用于
of course- interpersonal relationships.
人际关系领域
It applies in the realm of friendships.
它适用于友情
And it applies in the realm of leadership- the greatest leaders,
适用于提高领导能力
as Peter Drucker has illustrated,
像Peter Drucker阐述的那样
are not the people who are the most charismatic.
最伟大的领导不是最有魅力的
They are not the people who are the most engaging.
也不是最迷人的那些人
They are the people who have the highest levels of integrity.
而是极其诚实正直的人
These are the leaders
这样的领导
whom followers follow over time in a long term.
他的属下会长久追随他
So whether it's interpersonal group relationships
无论是团体间的人际关系
or individual relationships,
还是个人之间的私交关系
when we express ourselves,we are much more likely to thrive.
只要我们坦诚 就更可能被容纳接受
The second thing though is,that's important to keep in mind,
第二件应该时刻谨记的是
is that let's say I impress and I do such a good job of it
如果我给人留下了一个很好的印象
that the other person or the other group actually likes me.
使得这个人 或者这群人 都很喜欢我
It worked.I won.
这奏效了 我成功了
Well,have I? Who do they really like?
可这是真的吗?他们喜欢的是谁呢?
Do they like me or do they like that image,
他们喜欢的是我还是那个形象
that facade that I put on.
是我塑造的那个戴着面具的人吗?
In other words,it's not me that they really like.
换言之 他们喜欢的不是真正的我
And it may look like it.But it's pretense.
也许看起来是 但那不是真的
It's make-believe.It's not the real thing.In other words,I lose.
这喜欢是假象 换言之 我失败了
And it certainly cannot sustain itself over time.
而且这种假象也维持不了太久
So we have more likelihood of succeeding when we express;
所以说坦诚相待更可能持久
and zero likelihood of succeeding in the long term
而当我们的目标是给人留下一个好印象时
when our primary objective is impress.
这种情形持久的可能性为零
Now this does not mean going on first date
这并不是要你在第一次约会
and not trying to impress.
就放弃尝试给对方留下深刻印象
I mean I've not met anyone
我是说我还没见过谁没尝试过
who has not tried to impress on the first date or the 10th,
在首次甚至第十次约会 乃至第十次约会
or after 10 years- that's OK.However,
给对方留下深刻印象 这是可以的
what is the primary motivator in our time being together?
然而 共同生活最重要的动因是什么?
Just like we reveal,we open up,we share,
就像我们前面说的那样 敞开心扉
we also need to get and make active effort
我们还需要积极努力
to get to know our partner,to know what their favorite wine is,
去了解我们的伴侣 去了解他们爱喝的红酒
what their favorite flowers are;
喜欢的花
where they like to be tickled,where they like to be touched;
他们喜欢哪里被咯吱 哪里喜欢被触碰
what are their fears,what are their desires;
他们怕什么 渴望什么
when is it a good time to maybe give their own space,
什么时候该给他们一些独处的空间
when is it a good time to talk to them,
什么时候该和他们沟通
when is it a good time to touch them.
什么时候该触碰他们
And all these things take time.
所有这些都需要时间
It doesn't happen on the first date.
这不可能在首次约会时实现
It doesn't happen in the first year.
也不会在第一年里实现
And it doesn't all happen in the first ten years,or thirty years
不会在头10年或30年全部实现
That's what it means to create a lifelong thriving relationship
这意味着我们要用一生的时间
that we get to know the other person throughout our lives.
去了解对方 营造一生的美好恋情
My grandfather and grandmother,my role models,
我的祖父祖母
when it comes to relationships,
是我在感情方面的榜样
got to know each other deeper and better after 50 years as well.
他们在一起50年后 还在继续了解对方
They did thrive; they were thriving.
他们的感情很好
They did not succeed; they were succeeding,growing together.
他们的感情还没圆满 而是正在圆满
David Schnarch:
David Schnarch说过
"Intimacy is about letting yourself really be known,
"亲密就是让你自己被真正的了解
including parts that you or your partner don't like.
即使是你或你伴侣不喜欢的 也要被了解
But it's not just about letting 'warts' be known.
但这并不代表坦露的都是缺点
It often involves showing strengths you've been hiding,too.
有时也会是一直没发现的优点
Most approaches
大部分方法
focus on getting your partner's validation and acceptance
都专注于让你的伴侣 在你坦露时
when you disclose.
认同和接受你
But you can't count on this,and if you try,
但你不能寄希望于此 如果你心存这样的意图
it inherently limits self-disclosure
那么你坦露心声时必然有所掣肘
because you won't say things your partner won't validate.
因你只会说那些让你的伴侣认可的话
Resolving gridlock requires intimacy
打破僵局需要亲密关系
based on validating yourself."
这基于认可你自己"
Many,if not most,couples counselors,sex therapists believe
大多数婚姻咨询师 性治疗师认为
that the most important thing in a relationship,
一段恋情中最重要的
in a healthy long relationship is that
一段健康长久的恋情中最重要的是
the partners validate one another.
伴侣间彼此认可
And that is important.
这很重要
Of course I want to be validated by my partner.
我当然想被对方认可
Of course I validate my partner.
我当然认可我的伴侣
However,that's not the foundation of a healthy relationship.
然而这不是健康恋情的基础
And this is where most therapists,
而这是很多治疗师
most couples are and this is where I was wrong-
很多夫妻以及我曾犯过的错误
not understanding the foundation is to be known,
没有认识到被了解才是基础
whether it's in a romantic relationship
无论是在一段恋情中
or a relationship with friends.
还是与朋友的友情中
You see when you disclose,when you disclose,
当你坦露心声时
you are taking a risk.
你是冒着风险的
And very often,
而且很多时候
it leads to a conflict,a disagreement,disease in a relationship
这会引发冲突 破坏感情
However usually,not always,
然而通常 几率不是特别高
but usually-that is a temporary disease.
但通常 这只是短暂的破坏
On the other hand,
另一方面
if you disclose over time and you open up and you share,
若你长期坦诚 敞开胸怀
that's when you lead to long lasting,
这会引领你走向长久的感情
positive consequences to the relationship.
对恋情是有积极效果的
So on the one hand,when you disclose,
一方面来看 你坦诚时
it's uncomfortable by definition.
肯定会觉得不舒服
If it's comfortable,then it wouldn't be hard,
舒服的话也就不难了
wouldn't be real disclose.
也就不算真正的坦诚
It's difficult in the short term,
短期来看这是很难的
but in a long term,it leads to growth.
但从长远看 它能助长感情
So the question is what do you want?
关键在于你想要什么?
Do you want a temporary feeling-good?-
要短暂的舒服感觉?
Oh you are validated; you are wonderful.
你被认可了 你很棒
Let me impress and show you how terrific I am.
我来让你看看我有多优秀
Because it feels good to be validated.
因为被认可的感觉很好
Or are you looking for long-term thriving
还是你想要一段长久而美好的
interpersonal friendships or romantic relationships?
友情或是恋情?
That is the question.
这是个问题
Now I said earlier and I spoke about it a couple of months ago
接下来的话我几个月前就讲过
and I want to repeat it:
现在我想再重申一次
how it changed my relationship with my students,
我是怎样改变与学生的关系的
how it changed,transformed my teaching.
怎样转变我的教学方式
Because when I started to teach,my main goal-
因为最初教学时 我的主要目标是
whether it was explicit and at the time,it was explicit,
不管讲得是否清楚明白 当时确实很清楚
but mostly,on the subconscious level was to be validated.
但潜意识里最主要是想被认可
I really wanted my students to like me.
我真的很想让我的学生喜欢我
That was my primary goal,my primary objective.
那是我的主要目标
Over time,as David Schnarch specifically
慢慢的 看了很多人的著作
as well as looking other people's work
尤其是David Schnarch的书
such as Parker Palmer's "The courage to Teach",
还有Parker Palmer的"教学的勇气"
my objective changed to be known.
我的目标变为了被了解
This is my mantra now.
这是我现在的咒语了
Everyday before I stand here and talk to you,
每天上讲台前
every single day I think about and read my mantra.
我天天想着并念着我的咒语
In fact on the first page of my notes-
其实这就写在我的笔记本第一页
these are my notes,my cheat sheet.
这些是我的笔记 我的小抄
On the top- "be known".Every day.
第一行字就是"被了解" 每天都是
To be known rather than to be validated-
被了解而非被认可
that transforms my relationship with my students
这改变了我与学生的关系
and my teaching for various reasons.
以及教学方式 原因有下
First of all,it's so stressful enervating to think constantly
首先,老是想着
"I have to impress whether it's with my romantic partner
"我得让给他们觉得我很厉害 无论是对于我的伴侣
or you know,650 or 1000 students".
还是一千个学生" 压力太大了
It's difficult.There's a lot of pressure there.
这样很难 带给我太多压力了
It is much easier to stand up here and say "OK.
而若是站在这里说
What I want the students to do is to get to know me better."
"我想让我的学生更了解我"就简单多了
And that means to get to know the field that
这也意味着要了解
I'm so passionate and so caring about.
那个我非常喜欢和关心的领域
I want them to know me better.So I feel so much lighter about it.
我想要他们的了解 这让我觉得轻松
I feel so much lighter about it in my interaction with Tammy,
当我想被Tammy了解 而不是让她有个好印象
when it's about being known rather than impressing,
让她认可我时 我觉得和她在一起
rather than being validated.
轻松多了
That's the first important thing.
这是第一个要点
The second thing about trying to impress constantly is
长期想取悦别人的缺点是
if we put on a fa?ade and act and then I tried- tried-
若我们带着面具 且不断不断地试着
if I want to be validated constantly,to seem perfect
让自己被认可 看起来很完美
so that the students really like me and approve of me.
以便让学生喜欢我认可我
But then what I'm doing is that I'm hurting the students as well.
但这样做的同时也伤害到了学生
Because if I'm good at it,if I'm good at putting on a fa?ade
因为若我擅于演戏伪装
and depicting this perfect teacher,
扮演一个完美老师的角色
I'm being a terrible role model,
我就变成一个很差劲的榜样
which in the long term will only hurt the students.
久而久之会伤害到学生
Because that thing doesn't exist.
因为那个完美的我并不存在
And if anyone is inspired to this perfection,
如果有人想向这个完美的形象看齐
whether in a relationship,whether on the individual level,
无论是感情中还是在个人问题上
it is inevitably a prescription for perfectionism
都不可避免地通往完美主义
hence for failure,hence for unhappiness.
也是通往失败与不幸
Or if I'm here to be known,
除非我是想被了解
which means my weaknesses,my failures-
也就是说我的缺点 我的失败之处
whether it's my failure in Cambridge,my failure here,
不管是在剑桥还是在哈佛的失败
whether it's the anxiety,then you'll see a real person-
或是我的焦虑 你们会见到真实的我
whether it's the mistakes,you'll see a real person.
或是犯错误 你们见到的是真实的我
And that's a much better teacher,
这样的我是一个更好的老师
much more accessible I hope than the fa?ade,
相较于那个完美形象 更平易近人
perfect to thereabout to be validated.
好过那个被认可的我
And again,beyond the fact,it is so much fun for me being here.
除此以外 这样的我也更快乐
Because what I'm doing now is sharing with you.
因为我在这里与你们分享
I'm sharing my part of self with you.
我在分享自己的一部分内心世界
And I'm sharing the field that
我与大家分享的
I'm so passionate about and care about so much.
是我非常喜欢和关心的
To be known,to be known rather than to be validated.
被了解而非被认可
Easier said than done.
说起容易做来难
But the benefits,especially the long term benefits are immense.
但是利大于弊 尤其是长远来看
Absolutely immense.
好处远远大于弊处
The third point is about allowing for conflict in a relationship.
第三点是要允许恋情中出现冲突
You see one of the misunderstandings about healthy relationships
关于健康恋情的一个误解是
is that those relationships don't have conflict- they don't fight
健康恋情没有冲突 没有争吵
The gold standard is a conflict free relationship.
五星级的恋情不会发生冲突
And that's a serious misunderstanding.
这是一个很严重的误解
John Gottman has done a lot of work in this area.
John Gottman曾对此做过很多研究
One of the things that he showed was that
他得出的结论之一是
there is not one right relationship.
不存在所谓唯一的标准恋情
And that also means different relationships look differently
这也意味着每段恋情看起来都不同
from outside or from the inside.
无论外人看来 还是自己看
Some relationships thrive and they are very quiet.
有一些恋情美好而安宁
Some relationships thrive and are extremely volatile.
有一些恋情则美好却激烈
Both can succeed.
两种都可持续下去
There is no one right form of relationship.
恋情没有统一的正确形式
There are numerous permutations and variations on this.
恋情可以有无数种模式及不同之处
But there is one right relationship,
但健康恋情都有一个共同之处
one thing that Gottman has found
Gottman发现的一个共同之处
is that in all those relationships-
那就是在所有的恋情中
whether they are volatile or very peaceful and quiet,
无论是激烈的还是非常平和安宁的
or somewhere in between,they all have conflicts.
或是两者兼之的恋情 都有争执
And on average- again this is average,
而且平均来看 只是平均来看
because you know it can be 10 to 1.
因为有些人可能是10:1
It can also be 3 to 1.
有些人可能是3:1
But on average,
但是平均来看
they have 1 conflict for each 5 positive interactions.
每5次积极互动就会有一次争执
Now it doesn't mean now going home and telling your partner,
这并不是让你回家去和伴侣说
"you know we've already had 7 good interactions.
"我们已经有了7次积极互动了
Let's fight."
现在该吵架了"
Certainly not that.But that is what he's seen,
绝不是这样 但这是他研究发现的
when he studied hundreds,thousands of thriving couples.
当他研究了成百上千的和睦夫妻后
That was more or less
差不多这是
the average of conflict per positive interaction.
积极互动与争执冲突的平均比率
This statistics by the way helped me a lot.
这个数据启发到我
Because whenever Tammy and I used to fight,-
因为过去只要Tammy和我发生争吵
and yes we do fight at times,I used to say,"oh,what's wrong?"
我们也会争吵 我就会说"这是怎么了?"
Versus "now it's OK.It's natural.
而不是说"这很正常 不用担心
Let's see how we can resolve it,
看看该怎么解决这冲突
what we can learn from it,how we can grow from it."
从中学到些什么 怎样改进"
It doesn't mean I enjoy it,that we seek conflict.
这并不是说我喜欢冲突
It's awful.And sometimes it hurts very deeply.
冲突不好 有时很伤感情
But at the same time to understand it's natural.
但同时要理解到这是正常的
And just like we give ourselves the permission
就像我们允许自己
to be human on an individual level,
有个人的不足之处一样
it's important that
我们要允许我们的关系
we give our relationship the permission to be human and humane.
存在不足 这是很重要的
People who have that 5 to 1 ratio,
那些实现了5:1比率的人们
again more or less usually have the thriving relationship.
基本上都有一段美好恋情
People who have a lot less than 1 to 5 ratio,meaning 100 to 1,
而那些低于此比率 如100比1的
the relationship in the long term does not thrive,nor do people
这样的感情并不能长久地美好下去
who have many more conflicts than positive interactions.
那些冲突多于积极互动的伴侣也维持不下去
So neither extremes are good.
完全不吵不好 经常吵也不好
The importance of conflict is that it immunizes us.
冲突的重要性在于它使我们免疫
Let's look at the natural or physiological level of immunity.
先来看自然或生理上的免疫
What would happen to a person,
若把一个出生的婴儿放入消过毒的
just born and put into a oxygen tank not- which is sterilized-
储氧箱 而不把他抱出来
and not taken out of that sterilized oxygen tank?
这个孩子会怎样呢?
What would happen if say after 2 years,or 3 years,or 10 years,
比如说两三年甚至十年后
that baby,now no longer a baby
孩子长大了 离开洁净的环境
is taken out of that perfect surrounding into the real world?
回到真实的世界生活 他会怎样呢?
That person is very likely to get ill.
他很有可能会生病
Very likely to get seriously ill.
且很可能是重病
Why? Because it's not healthy to be in a sterilized environment
为什么?因为在无菌环境里生长
on the physiological level.
就生理上说是不健康的
Because every time you get ill,
因为每次你生病
or every time you are exposed to pollutions or bacteria,
或是每次你暴露于污染与细菌中
your body actually strengthens.
你的身体都会因为产生抗体而变强
The same in a relationship.
这对恋情也是同样的道理
If you are not exposed to conflicting relationship,
如果你的恋情从不发生冲突
over time,over time the relationship will not strengthen.
久而久之 恋情无法得到巩固加强
You'll be weak;it'll be unable to sustain
你会变得脆弱 当冲突无可避免时
the inevitable conflict that will arise.
恋情就会难以维持
So conflict immunizes us.It is important.
所以说冲突使我们免疫 这很重要
And we'll talk about in what ways or what the conflict looks like
再谈一下冲突的种类与形式
Because not every conflict is healthy.
因为不是每种冲突都有益
The key that Gottman talks about
Gottman说过关键不在于
is not to take away or eliminate the negative,
消除负面的东西
but rather to accentuate,to strengthen the positive.
而是要强调巩固积极的东西
So in relationships that
所以对于那些不成功的恋情
don't thrive where there's too much fighting,-
那些经常发生争吵的恋情
relationships that are here.
像这样的恋情
Just accentuate the positive.
强调积极方面
If you are here and there are no conflicts,well that means
而若是处于这种无冲突恋情
maybe we are suppressing things- emotions,disagreements.
很可能你们在压抑 压抑感受 分歧
In other words,we are not being known and we need to move on,
换言之 我们没被了解 我们需要改进
and reveal ourselves,open up and share.
坦诚 敞开心扉 彼此分享
Here are some ways of accentuating the positive.
这里有几种强调积极方面
So you remember in the book of,on,in "Happier",
大家记得那本"更幸福"的书
I talk about happiness boosters.
我讲过的关于幸福助力器
These are mini activities-
有一些细小的事情
could be anywhere from a minute to 3 hours of doing things
可以是几分钟也可以是几小时的事
are both meaningful and pleasurable to us.
能让我们快乐 也很有意义
So just like we have happiness boosters
就像我们借助幸福助力器
that can have a trickle effect for the rest of our lives.
滴水穿石地提高我们一辈子的幸福感
We can also have love boosters.
我们也可以借助爱情助力器
There is a story about Albert Einstein and Ludwig van der Rohe.
有一个关于爱因斯坦与Ludwig van der Rohe的故事
Ludwig van der Rohe was one of the founders of quantum physics.
Ludwig van der Rohe是量子物理学的创始人之一
And when Ludwig van der Rohe wrote Einstein a letter
Ludwig van der Rohe写信给爱因斯坦
saying to him "you know I want to introduce you
说"我想你进入量子物理
to this new fascinating field of quantum physics.
这个神奇而美妙的新领域
I want your support."
我需要您的支持"
Einstein was a big shot at the time.
爱因斯坦当时颇有声望
Einstein responded with a letter.
他回了一封信
And in the letter said to Ludwig van der Rohe:
信里对Ludwig van der Rohe说
"I'm not interested in quantum physics.
"我对量子物理不感兴趣
What I'm not interested are...I'm not interested in the details.
因为我对细节上的东西不感兴趣
What I am interested in is what God thought about
我感兴趣的是上帝在创造世界时
when He created the world.
他在想着什么
I'm not interested in the details.
我对细节没兴趣
I am interested in is what God thought about
我只关心上帝创造世界时的
when He created the world."-
他在想着什么"
to which Ludwig van der Rohe wrote back,
Ludwig van der Rohe回信说
saying,"God is in the details."
"上帝就在细节中"
The same with love.Love is in the details.
爱情也是这样 爱情就在细节中
Love is not in that one week or two months
爱情不在一周或一个月的
around the world cruise;
环游世界中
love is not in that 5 carat diamond ring.
爱情不在五克拉的钻戒里
Yes these things are wonderful;
这些东西是很美妙
they are certainly to a spike in well being,
也确实激发了幸福感
sometimes to a spike in love,
有时甚至激发了爱情
but they are not what sustains a happy relationship.
但它们不能维持一段美好的感情
What sustains a happy relationship are the details.
能够长期维持幸福恋情的是细节
The little things.
是那些微小的事情
The day to day rituals,the touch,the gaze,the meal together.
是每天的生活常规 触碰 凝视 共进晚餐
Mini love boosters also sustain.
迷你爱情助力器也能维持
I got this idea from Peter Fraenkel
这是我从Peter Fraenkel学来的
who is From the Ackerman Family Center in New York.
他是纽约Ackerman家庭服务中心的
And what he talks about are 30 seconds pleasure points
他讲的是一天里的
throughout the day,
30秒钟的幸福点
whether it's a passionate kiss,
无论是一个激吻
whether it's just a hug where you just hold one another,
或只是一个单纯的拥抱
whether it's just sending a text message to your partner
或是发给伴侣的一条短信
saying how much you love them and miss them- the little things.
告诉他们你有多爱他们多想他们这类小事
And what they found
他们发现
was these little things made the big difference.
正是这些小事产生重大影响
Again,yes,the big things also make a difference.
当然 大事也能产生影响
I'm not belittling them.But that just leads to a spike.
我不是贬低大事 但那只能导致激变
To sustain happiness it takes time,and it takes work.
而维持幸福需要长久的努力
It takes commitment.
需要奉献
A relationship is made extraordinary
感情的维系主要是靠
by focusing on these details on day to day activities.
注重这些日常琐碎的小事
And how we do that? We demonstrate interest,
我们怎么做到呢?我们表现出我们的关心
by asking "so how is your day sweetheart",
我们问"你今天过得怎样?"
or "tell me more about what you have just done",
或"讲讲你刚做了什么"
or "what have you been thinking",
或"你在想什么"
or you know "you look a little bit down- anything I can do".
或"你不太高兴啊 我能做什么"
Demonstrate interest.Create love maps.
表现出关心 画爱情地图
Get to know the other person- what they like;
去了解对方 他喜欢什么
what they don't like; and how they like it.
不喜欢什么 有多喜欢
Again,the little things such as touching,
就是那些小事 比如触碰
such as smiling,such as flowers,
微笑 送花
such as remembering the important dates,men.
记得重要的日子
Today is much easier.
现在这些简单多了
You know we have the computer reminding us- have many reminders.
我们有电脑提醒我们
Talking from personal experience.
就我个人经验来讲
Pay compliments.Pay compliments to your partners.
称赞 称赞对方
You know don't take for granted.
不要以为一切都是理所应当的
Remember the word appreciate- two meanings.
记得我们讲过感激 两个意思
To pay compliment to someone- oh you look wonderful;
其中之一就是称赞某人 "你看来棒极了"
oh this is so great- thank you so much for doing;
这太好了 谢谢你做这些
thank you for thinking of me.
谢谢你想到我
Paying compliments- appreciating makes the good appreciates.
带有感激的赞赏是最好的感激
When we don't appreciate,when we don't pay compliments,
当我们不懂得感激与赞赏时
the good depreciates.
美好会贬值 马克吐温说过
Mark Twain: "I can live for two months on a good compliment."
"一个好的赞赏能让我高兴两个月"
Don't take him literally though.
不要只理解了他的字面意思
Let me share with you a story.
给你们讲个故事
This is my father in law and his wife.
这是我的岳父与岳母的故事
My father in law is a graduate at Harvard law school-
我的岳父毕业于哈佛法学院
very bright,very smart and married to- his name is Amie.
很聪明很有才华 他叫Amie
Married to a lovely woman Rachel- Rahel(Hebrew pronunciation).
娶了一位可爱的女人Rachel Rahel(希伯来语发音)
And they went on a date.
有一次他们约会
Rahel- Rachel was wearing a beautiful dress.
Rachel穿了件很美的裙子
And they walked into a party and they spent a whole night.
他们去参加一个派对 整晚都在那里
And there were so many people.It was a lovely evening.
派对上人很多 那是一个美妙的夜晚
And at the end of the evening,they went back home.
派对结束后他们回到家
And Rachel asked Amie,
Rachel问Amie
you know she said,"Amie,you know the whole night,
"Amie 今晚整个晚上
after getting compliments about how wonderful I look,
我得到了无数赞美 说我很漂亮
how ravishing the dress is,how radiant I look,
说我裙子很美 很容光焕发
I got it from everyone except for from you."
大家都赞美我 却惟独你没有"
Now remember Amie is a Harvard law graduate-
要知道Amie是哈佛法学毕业生
very smart,very quick on his feet.
非常聪明 反应灵敏
One of the leading lawyers in Israel.So he said,
他是以色列的一流律师 他说道
"Rahel- Rachel,do you remember when a couple of months ago,
"Rahel 你还记得几个月前
I told you how beautiful,how gorgeous you were?"
我告诉你 你有多美丽动人吗?"
And she said,"yes.Of course I remember."
她说"我当然记得"
He said,"well until further notice,you are beautiful."
他说"直到另行通知前 你都那么美丽动人"
Now.[Laugh] Now that almost worked.
这句话几乎能过关了
The problem was Rahel- Rachel is also a lawyer.
问题是Rachel也是个律师
Very bright.Very successful.
同样聪明同样成功
And she said to him,
她对她说
"Amie,sweetheart,until further notice,you are on the couch."
"Amie 直到另行通知前 你都睡沙发"
So don't wait.Don't wait to be asked to give compliments.
所以不要等别人开口 你才赞美他们
Give it.It's free.
主动赞美 又不花钱
And yet though it's free,
然而虽不花钱
in the ultimate currency it is invaluable.Invaluable.
但它的价值却是不可估量的
Because we get so much out of it-
因为它令我们获益甚多
the giver as well as the receiver.
赞美与被赞美的人都获益
You know the No.1 predictor of therapeutic relationships
最能预测一段治疗关系是否成功
the No.1 predictor of the success of therapist,
最能预测一个治疗师
of psychologist or social worker or psychiatrist is empathy.
心理学家 社工是否成功的 是移情
How well you are able to understand,to empathize,
你有多理解多同情
to identify with your client.
多认同你的客户
It's no different in romantic relationships.
在恋情中也一样
Do I really listen to my partner? Do I really look at my partner?
我真的在聆听我的伴侣吗?我真的在看我的伴侣吗?
Do I demonstrate genuine interest
我真的对我伴侣做的事
in what my partner is doing,feeling? And how they are?
表现出真诚的关心吗?他们好吗?
Do I really really want to get to know them?
我真的想要了解他们吗?
Because if we don't have that,
因为如果不是这样
it is very difficult to sustain a long term thriving relationship
要维持长久美好的恋情是很难的
And finally,sex is important for long term thriving relationship
最后 性在长久美好恋情中很重要
It does not have to come before marriage;
性不一定要在婚前发生
does not have to come before there is a life long commitment-
或者等到彼此承诺厮守一生才发生性关系
marriage or other.
这厮守可以是结婚也可以不是
It can; it often does in our world.
可以是婚姻 在现实生活中也经常是婚姻
And either way is fine- either choice.
是不是结婚都行
However,for the long term success of the relationship,
然而 对于长期恋情的成功延续
it is also important to have the physical aspect.
生理方面也很重要
It's very rare- it exists-
极少的情况下 也存在
but it's very rare to a romantic relationship
也存在极少的恋情
without the physical component.
是没有生理方面的因素的
Cause that's one of the distinguishing characteristics
生理因素是区分爱与深厚友情的
between that and a deep friendship,for example.
一个显著特征
Love at its- or rather sex at its highest is love made concrete.
爱情 准确地说 性的至高点使爱具体化
Love made concrete.
使爱具体化
That is why we talk about making love.
这也是为什么我们会说做爱
It's the concretization of the emotion,of that abstract notion.
它是感情 是抽象的爱的具体化
The important thing here is,
生理方面很重要的一点是
as every other areas of the relationship,healthy communication.
健康的交流 就像别的感情一样
Because very often we reveal ourselves,we share of ourselves
因为我们经常坦露自己 分享自己
in the bedroom more than in any other place,
在卧室远多过在其他地方
whether it's physically or emotionally or cognitively.
无论是肉体上 还是情感上 还是认知上
That's where we open up.
那是我们敞开心怀的地方
That's when we are literally metaphorically naked.
那是我们真正赤裸相对的地方
And communication is important
交流是很重要的
because very often there are differences in expectations.
因为人与人的期望值是不同的
And there is no one right prescription here-
这也没什么统一的规定
OK,you know sex 5 times a week,the best relationships;
一周5次性生活 最好的恋情
3,not bad; 1,OK.
三次 不错 一次 合格
No,there are fantastic relationships where it's you know,
不 有很多美妙的恋情
once a day or twice a month- sorry,or once a week.
一天一次或一个月二次 对不起 或者一星期一次
There are wonderful relationship...[Laugh]
有一些美妙的恋情
Or there is every day 3 times.
或是一天三次
No.There is no one right prescription.
不 对此没有统一的规定
I don't know what I said was funny,
不知道我刚才说的哪句好笑
but I'll have to watch it after
不过我课后会看一下的
because I'm sure Freud is watching now.
因为我相信佛洛依德现在一定也在看着
And the important thing is to communicate.
最重要的是交流
Because it is a source of conflict.
因为它是冲突的根源
It is a potential source of conflict.
是冲突的潜在根源
It doesn't have to be.
并不必一定如此
Let me show you a quick video
来看一段短视频
just to get the attention off me for a minute.
注意力从我这里转移开一下
From Woody Allen.
这是伍迪艾伦的影片
[Movie: Annie Hall (1977)- subtitles on the screen]
[电影：安妮霍尔(1977)-屏幕上字幕]
That day in Brooklyn was the last day
我记得对上一次开心的时候
I remember having a good time.
是在布鲁克林的那天
We never have any laughs anymore.
我们再也不敞怀大笑了
I've been moody and dissatisfied.
我一直情绪低落 欲求不满了
How often do you sleep together? Do you have sex often?
你们多久做爱一次?性生活频繁吗?
Hardly ever.Maybe three times a week.
很少 一周三次吧
Constantly.I'd say three times a week.
经常做 一周三次吧
Like the other night,Alvy wanted to have sex.
前几天晚上 Alvy想做爱
She would not sleep with me the other night,you know?
前几天晚上她不想和我睡 你知道吗?
I don't know.
我不知道
I mean Six months ago I would have done it just to please him.
如果是六个月前 为让他开心我会做
I tried everything.
我什么都试过了
I put on soft music and my red light bulb.
放轻音乐 浅红色的灯光
But the thing is since our discussions here,
但是自从我们来这里讨论后
I feel I have a right to my own feelings.
我觉得我有权顾及自己的感受
I think you would have been happy,
我觉得你听到这个会高兴
because I really asserted myself.
因为我真的能坚持自我了
The incredible thing about it is,
最讽刺的是
I'm paying for her analysis and she's making progress,
我出钱让她看心理医生 她有改善了
and I'm getting screwed.
我却更糟糕了
I don't know.
我不知道
I feel so guilty,because Alvy is paying for it.
我觉得好内疚 因为Alvy出钱让我来看
So you know I do feel guilty if I don't go to bed with him.
所以不和他上床 让我内疚
But if I do go to bed with him,
但要是真的和他上床
it's like I'm going against my own feelings.
感觉像是我不顾及自己的感受
-I'm not making any progress.  -I can't win.
我没有进展 我赢不了
Sometimes I think I should live with a woman.
有时我觉得我该找个女人住
Dr.Tal Ben-Shahar: So hardly ever- 3 times a week.
"很少 一周三次"
Constantly- 3 times a week.Again,different perceptions.
"经常做 一周三次" 不同看法
Communication is important.Not any conflict is good.
沟通很重要 不是所有的冲突都是好的
There is positive as well as negative conflict.
冲突有积极的有消极的
Helpful research in this area
对这个问题的有用研究
comes actually from organizational behavior.
其实主要来自组织行为
Specifically,what research in organizational behavior shows
确切的说 组织行为研究表明
is that healthy inter-group or intra-group conflict
健康的组织内或组织外冲突
is cognitive conflict rather than affective conflict.
是认知冲突 而非情感冲突
Cognitive conflict is about focusing on the person's behavior,
认知冲突针对人的行为
or thoughts and ideas,and challenging those.
或思想 观念 对这些提出质疑
Unhealthy conflict is focusing on the person,on the emotions,
不健康的冲突 注重于人 情感
on who they are.
他们自身
And when I attack someone for who they are-
而当我攻击某人自身
the person,the emotion,that is not healthy-
那个人本身及情感时 这是不健康的
not for a group,not for couples .
无论是组织 还是夫妻
At the same time,
与此同时
I can disagree with,can have conflict when it comes,
当针对观念 想法 行为时
when we focus on the ideas,the thought and the behavior.
我可以不赞同 可以发生争执
Let me show you an example.
举例来说
Here is an example of focusing on the person.
这是一个针对人自身的例子
You are so inconsiderate.
你不体谅别人
This is not the behavior; this is the person.
这不是针对行为的 而是针对人的
Focusing on the behavior:
而针对行为的是
do you mind putting down the toilet seat when you are done?
你用完马桶后把坐垫放下来好吗?
It may be as the result of the same thing-
这两句话可能是由同一件事引发的
you know,you didn't put the toilet seat down.
就是你没把马桶坐垫放下来
One response- you are so inconsiderate.
一个反应是 "你不体谅别人"
That's the person.versus the behavior.
这就是针对人和针对行为的例子
Another example.You are such a slob.
另一个例子 "你这个懒鬼
You promised to throw away the garbage.
答应了要扔垃圾的
I can't trust you.That is an attack on the person.
我不能信任你了" 这是针对个人了
Yeah I think so.
我觉得是这样的
Versus it upsets me to return to a dirty home
与之相对的是"你说过要扔垃圾却没有做到
after we agreed that you throw away the garbage.
让我回家就看到乱糟糟 很恼火"
Same event.
一样的事
Very different approach,
不同的态度
very different results to these criticisms.
这两种评价带来的后果也不同
In addition to challenging behavior rather than person- sorry.
除了质疑行为而非个人以外…抱歉
It is important to avoid hostility,insult and contempt.
尽量避免恶意 侮辱及蔑视
John Gottman talks about this a lot in his research.
John Gottman在其研究中多次提及
And he says,one,he can predict divorce with 94 percent accuracy
他说自己预言离婚有94%的准确度
as I mentioned last time.
就像我上次提到的那样
Unheard of in the social sciences.
在社会科学中从没有过这么高的准确度
And he can do it based on whether he sees-
他判断的根据是
in the disagreements,in the conflicts
是否在争吵和冲突中看到…
and he asks the partners to describe their conflict.
他让夫妻描述他们的冲突
And very often they start fighting as he observes them.
通常他们在他的观察下开始争执
When there is hostility,when there is contempt,
当出现恶意及蔑视
very often that is a bad sign- doesn't always lead to divorce.
通常是坏的预示 但不总是导致离婚
Certainly not.But it is a bad sign.
绝对不是 但确实是坏的预示
It is a bad sign in terms of the long term likelihood of success,
这不仅是在感情能否长期维持的坏预示
but it's also a bad sign
这还是在享受
in terms of the current enjoyment of the relationship.
现有恋情方面的坏预示
So it is important to keep these insults away,
所以有必要避免这种侮辱的发生
to focus on the person,to validate the person,
避免针对人身 认可本人
to appreciate the person,and then to disagree with the behavior
尽量赞赏对方 仅对其行为
or with the ideas and the thinking.
或是其想法观念不苟同
The key is to keep these disputes private,meaning:
还有很关键的一点是 私下才争吵 意思是说
it is difficult enough to fight in a relationship;
本来恋情中的争吵就很不好
it is extraordinary difficult
若是再引来尴尬羞愧
when embarrassment is also associated with it.
就更糟糕了
So couples who shout at one another when there are others.
所以夫妻在有外人时 吼叫对方
Or when they show contempt,when other friends are there.
或者有朋友在场时 轻视对方
That is extremely destructive,extremely unhelpful.
这是非常具有破坏力的 极其危险的
So to keep these intimate moments
所以让争吵私下化
that can potentially lead to growth private.
能潜在的让私密关系好起来
Finally we can learn a lot from conflicts in gay couples.
最后 我们能从同性恋情中学到很多
As I mentioned last time,
像我上次提到的那样
John Gottman has studied gay couples a great deal.
John Gottman研究了很多同性恋情侣
And one of the interesting things that he found
他发现了一件很有趣的事情
was that they fight differently.
他们争吵起来很独特
Now the interesting thing here-
有趣的地方在于
it would not have been interesting if that was just between women
若是两个女人争吵　那没什么新奇的
The interesting thing is that he found it also between men.
有意思的是 这也发生在男同性恋间
Because women generally are better at fights than men.
因为女人通常比男人擅于争执
And there is actually a physiological reason for it.
也确实有生理上的原因
There is a physiological reason
这是有生理上的原因
because men when they are attacked for example,
举例来说 男人受到言论攻击时
or they feel attacked or threatened,or disapproved of,
或觉得别人在攻击 威胁 或不赞同他们时
actually have a much more powerful,physiological response to it,
他们其实会有更强烈的生理反应
which is why men are more likely for example to switch off.
这也是为什么男人通常吵着吵着就不吵了
It's not just because they are men;
这不仅是因为他们是男人
it 's because their real physiological differences there;
这是因为有生理上的差异
where a woman,for example,
而女人 举例来说
who is criticized,will feel it- no on enjoys it.
被批评时 虽不会喜欢
But the men- again these are all average.
但相对于男人…这是普遍来说
It doesn't mean all men or all women.
并不是指所有男女
But on average,men will feel it in a much more intense way
普遍来说 男人对此更紧张
and then will try to protect themselves.
他们会想要保护自己
And one of the ways of protecting ourselves is by switching off,
而方法之一就是不跟你吵了
avoiding rather than coping.
逃避 而不是应对
Whereas women are much more comfortable
而女人对争吵更适应
even on the physiological level-
甚至是生理上的更适应
I'm not talking about the interpretation of that physiology.
我不是说心理所反映的生理感受
But on the physiological level,
而是说单纯的生理层面上
they are much more comfortable handling and dealing
女人更善于处理应对
with this disease or discomfort of an argument.
这种争执的弊端及不适
So the first thing is to know it,
所以首先要知道的是
whether you are a man and you understand- I shouldn't switch.
无论你是否是男人 你要明白你不该逃避
I know I'm uncomfortable.It's part of my nature.I accept it.
我知道我不舒服 这是天生的 要接受
And then you can cope rather than avoid.
接着你便能处理 而非避免
Or with women,to have more empathy and understand that
而女人 要明白
their partner's experience is not the same as their experience.
她们的伴侣与自己的感触不同
But here is the interesting thing- in gay couples,men or women,
但这里有意思的是 在同性恋情中
we see an enhanced,a better ability to disagree.
男女同性恋 都能更好应对分歧
For example,how do they do it? First thing,
他们怎么做呢? 第一
more positive,more humor,more affection,more touching,
更积极 更幽默 更多爱意与触碰
whether it's the men or women.
无论是男的还是女的同性恋者
And that helps to dissolve,
这对解决分歧很有帮助
to relax some of the tension that exists.
能够缓解紧张的气氛
Again,both for men and for women couples.
男女同性恋者都是
The negativity is less often taken personally.
人身攻击的情况较少
So even if there is a serious disagreement- well,
所以即使有了严重分歧
I understand this is a part of growth.
我理解这是感情成长的一部分
This is important to keep in mind that
记住这点很重要
yes we may not be enjoying ourselves now.
这一刻我们的确不喜欢
It is a serious fight.
这是严重的争执
But what can I learn from it? what are we going to learn?
但我能学到什么?我们要学什么?
How are we going to grow?
我们怎样成长?
Because I understand the conflict is a natural,inevitable,
因为我明白 冲突是正常 不可避免的
important part of our relationship.
这是我们恋情中的一部分
Gay couples do it more;
同性恋情侣都能做到
no reason why heterosexual couples can't do it more.
异性恋情侣没理由做不到
Simply by reminding.
只要这么想想就行了
And finally,there's more attention to the other side,
最后 要多关心对方
to calm down,to understand,to be empathic,
冷静下来 理解对方的感受
whether it's men or women.
无论男女
To be empathic and understand and soothe.
要设身处地理解对方 让对方平静下来
And very often,just in a middle of conflict,
通常 就在争执中
saying something like,you know "I'm sorry" or just a hug.
说一些"我很抱歉" 或是一个拥抱
Or you know "it hurts me and I love you so much".
或"我很受伤也很爱你"
Just ways of soothing,
这些方法都能让对方平静下来
alleviating some of the pressure in the conflict.
减缓冲突带来的压力
Because conflicts are not easy.
因为冲突不是好事
Certainly not easy for gay couples either.
对同性恋情侣当然也不易
It's just being able to manage a conflict when it occurs.
只是他们能应对得好一些
Does not need to be peculiar to same sex relationships.
并不只是同性情侣才懂得处理冲突
You know we talked about- we know the golden rule:
我们讲过 黄金法则
do not do unto others what you would not have done unto yourself.
己所不欲 勿施于人
We talked about the platinum rule:
我们讲过白金法则
do not do unto yourself what you would not do unto others,
人所不欲 勿施于自
when we talked about perfectionism and the permission to be human
这是我们讲完美主义 和允许自己有不足时讲过的
So here is the Titanium rule: do not do unto those close to you
然后是钛规则 你不会对泛泛之交做的事
what you would not have done unto others who are not so close to you.
也千万不要对你亲密的人做
You know how often in the street or when you just met someone,
有多大的可能你会对
do you shout at them?
陌生人或刚认识的人大吼?
Or find other ways of showing contempt or insult?
鄙视他们 侮辱他们?
Being aggressive or passively aggressive?
挑衅别人?
How many times do you do that to strangers?
你对陌生人做过几次这种事?
I mean they really would have to do a terrible,
他们一定是对你做了极糟糕的事
awful thing for you to express contempt,
才让你表示出如此恶意轻视
or hostility,or anger toward them?
对他们大发雷霆
And yet on average,we do it so much more often-
然而平均下来 我们常常
again,not always,not everyone-
虽然不是人人都经常这样
but so many people do it so often with people close to them,
但是确有很多人这样对亲近的人
whether it's family members,whether it's a very close friend,
无论是家人还是亲密的朋友
whether it's romantic partners.
还是爱人
No justification for that.
没有理由这样做
Yes,it is also because we are more intimate with them,
没错 是因为我们与他们更亲近
because we feel more comfortable with them,but why?
因为和他们一起更舒适 但是为什么呢?
Why treat others better
为什么对外人
than we treat the people we love the most?
比对我们最爱的人反而要好?
Why treat the people we love the most worse
为什么对所爱之人
than we would treat others?
比对不相干的人要差?
There 's no justification.There can be conflict.
这无理可循 可以有争执
There will be conflicts.And it is important.
会有争执 且争执很重要
Question is how do you keep it on the cognitive behavior level
问题是你怎样将其保持在认知行为上
rather than the affective,emotional,contempt level?
而非情感的 感情的 蔑视的层面?
And that can make all the differences.
这会导致极大的不同
Essentially what we are talking about here
我们讲了这么多内容
when it comes to romantic relationships
在一段恋情中 最重要的
is cultivating a deep meaningful friendship.
是培养一份深厚的友情
John Gottman: "At the heart of my program is the simple truth
John Gottman说"我的方法的核心是一个简单的真理
that happy marriages are based on a deep friendship.
即幸福的婚姻基于深厚的友情之上
By this I mean a mutual respect for
这句话意味尊重对方
and enjoyment of each other's company.
享受与对方的相处
These couples tend to know each other intimately―
这些情侣能深入了解对方
they are well versed in each other's likes,dislikes,
他们熟知对方的喜恶
personality quirks,hopes,and dreams.
性格怪癖 理想与梦想
They have an abiding regard for each other
他们对彼此有着持久的尊敬
and express this fondness not just in the big ways,
不仅在大的问题上表达喜爱之情
but in little ways day in and day out."
也在日常琐碎间表达出来"
Love is in the details.
爱情就在于细节
It's about knowing the little things,the big things.
在于事无巨细的了解
It is about sharing and being known.
在于分享与被了解
That's what a healthy relationship is.And
这就是健康的恋情
that's how you can sustain passion in a relationship over years.
这就是你如何让恋情维持激情数年
And that's how you can continue to enjoy a passionate,
这就是你如何持续享受激情
sexual relationship,even though physiologically,
性关系 虽然在生理方面
maybe initially the natural inclination would be toward novelty,
一开始会很自然地倾向于新鲜体验
toward the "exotic is erotic".
"新鲜的才是激情的"
It doesn't have to be that way.
但不一定就要这样
It can be that way as well and that's natural.
当然可以是这样 这很自然
And that can the fantasies that you share.
可以用双方的幻想来体验一下新鲜
But ultimately for the long term relationship,
但是对于长久的恋情
passionate relationship,to be known rather than to be validated.
充满激情的恋情 最根本的是要被了解而非被认可
Finally the fourth component of the healthy relationship-
最后 关于健康恋情的第四点
I'll just touch it now
我现在先提一点
and we'll finish it up next week- positive perception.
然后在下周再讲完 积极认知
In a relationship,a healthy relationship
在一段恋情中 一段健康的恋情中
the partners have to be the benefit finders.
伴侣一定要做优点感知者
They have to appreciate one another.
他们要赞赏对方
Because remember if we don't appreciate,the good depreciates.
要记住若不懂赞赏对方 美好会贬值
If we don't appreciate what is working in a relationship,
如果我们不感激这段恋情中顺利的地方
pass the honeymoon phase,
过了蜜月期后
the relationship will enter a downward spiral.
恋情会急转直下
And unfortunately,that happens to most relationships.
不幸的是 这种情形常发生
Because we begin to take it for granted.
因为我们开始把好的东西视为理所当然
And if we take for granted a relationship,it withers and dies.
而当我们这么做时 恋情就会消逝
If we take for granted our own potential,
若我们将自己的潜力看做理所应当
that potential withers and dies.
那潜力会衰减乃至消亡
So benefit finding is important in a relationship.
所以说优点感知 对一段恋情很重要
To focus on the discipline of my partner
欣赏伴侣的自律
rather than on the rigidity.
而不是把自律看成固执
To focus on their sense of humor
欣赏伴侣的幽默感
rather than look at it as frivolous.
而不是把幽默看成耍滑头
Focusing on the good; focusing on what works.
把注意力放在优点上 放在顺利的地方上
And that is then accentuated.
这些优点就会加强
However successful thriving couples take this step further.
然而成功的幸福伴侣做得更好
They are not just benefit finders;
他们不仅是优点感知者
they have what Sandra Murray calls,positive illusions.
他们还有Sandra Murray所说的积极错觉
In other words,
换言之
they think of their partner more than other people think of them.
他们认为伴侣要比别人眼中还要好
So the experiment that Sandra Murray did was the following:
Sandra Murray做的实验如下
she asked couples to evaluate one another's strengths
她让情侣们评价另一半的优点
and then she asked other people
然后她再去叫那些
who are close to these two partners to evaluate their strengths.
与他们相熟的人们 评价他们的优点
And what she found was that couples who evaluated accurately,
她发现那些准确地评价对方的情侣
meaning they evaluated their partner in the same way as others-
也就是与朋友家人的评价差不多的
friends,family members evaluated them- they were OK.
他们的感情还算说得过去
They were OK together.
他们在一起过得凑和
Couples who evaluated one another's strengths on a lower level,
那些对伴侣优点评价得比别人还差的
meaning they didn't evaluate them as good,
也就是他们对彼此的评价不如
as strong,as powerful,as virtuous- whatever it was-
外人所认为的那么优秀 强大等
as other people did,whether it's family or friends,
不管是来自朋友还是家人的评价
these relationships did not last for long on average.
这些恋情一般持续不了很久
Couples who evaluated each other at a higher level,
而那些对彼此的评价
meaning as better than friends evaluated them,
要高于其朋友 或家人
as better than family evaluated them,
给予的评价的情侣
these couples' relationships were most likely to thrive
这些情侣的恋情最可能
and succeed over time.
持续且美好下去
And Sandra Murray called it- because
这部分人 Sandra Murray将其称为
they were not connected to the evaluation of other people,
因为他们对彼此的评价与外界不符
Sandra Murray called it "positive illusions".
Sandra Murray将其称为"积极错觉"
Now- or another term used Brad Little used this term,
或按Brad Little的说法是
having an "illusory glow" about them,
他们有着"虚幻的光辉"
seeing them as better than supposedly they really are.
认为彼此远比实际上要好
Now I agree partially with Sandra Murray.
我部分同意Sandra Murray的观点
I agree with her that it is important to have these high,
我同意她说的 对伴侣有积极的评价
more positive evaluations.
是很重要的
The one thing that I disagree with Murray
但我不同意她的是
is on the use of the word illusion.
对于错觉这一词汇的运用
Because I don't think that is an illusion.
因为我认为这不是错觉
In fact,it is very real.
事实上 这是真实的
It is very real because it becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy.
因为这成为一个自我实现的预言
And here I'm introducing a new term
在这里我引进一个新的术语
in addition to benefit finding,benefit creating.
除了优点感知 还有优点创造
Seeing things that were not there
看到不存在的优点 或是
or the other people had not seen and then making it real.
别人没看到的优点并让其成为现实
And think about in another domain.
想想教育界里的一个例子
Was Marva Collins detached?
Marva Collins脱离实际了吗?
Did Marva Collins have positive illusions about her students?
Marva Collins对她的学生有积极错觉了吗?
Not at all.
完全不是
I would argue the others,the other teachers were detached
我认为 是其他老师脱离切实了
because they didn't see that potential in their students.
因为他们没有看到学生身上的潜力
Marva Collins was very much connected.
Marva Collins非常切合实际
And she focused on the positive and created the benefits.
她关注于积极方面 并创造优点
Abraham Maslow: "Not only does love perceive potentialities
Abraham Maslow说过"爱不仅能感知潜力
but it also actualizes them."
而且还让其转换为现实"
Let me tell you a quick story about Tammy.
给你们讲个Tammy的小故事
And as I mentioned to you,Tammy is a consummate merit finder.
如我所说 Tammy是个完美的优点感知者
In fact,she is a merit creator.
事实上 她是个优点创造者
So this was at time when Tammy was 8 months pregnant.
这事发生在Tammy怀孕8个月的时候
Huge baby.Those of you who know David,he's a very big baby.
胎儿很大了 你们都见过David了 大宝宝
Like father,like son.
虎父无犬子
So this is 8 month pregnant
所以在怀孕8个月时
and Tammy takes me for one of those talks that
Tammy和我有过一段交谈
those of you in long term relationships know about.
你们谈过很久恋爱的人就会明白这谈话是怎样的了
And she says,"Tal,you know,this is getting really heavy.
她说"Tal 他变得越来越沉了
This is really difficult for me and I just need your help more.
这真的对我很难 我需要你更多帮助
You just need to help me a little bit more in the house."
你需要在家帮我一点小忙"
And I said to her,"fine."
我说"好的"
I felt so sheepish and so inconsiderate.
我感到很窘迫 觉得自己很不体贴
And I said,"I'm sorry.Fine.So what can I do?"
我说"抱歉 我能做什么?"
And she said,"you know shopping this afternoon would help.
她说"你可以今天下午去帮我买东西
I just can't carry these bags any more."
我再也拿不动那些大包小包了"
So I went to the Star Market.Filled up the entire refrigerator.
于是我去了超市 把冰箱塞满了
Not only brought the things home,
不仅是买回家
but actually put them in the refrigerator.
还把它们放进冰箱
Because I felt so guilty.
因为我觉得很内疚
And Tammy saw that and she said
Tammy看到后说
"you know thank you so much for doing it."
"太感谢你做的这一切了"
And I said to Tammy,
我对Tammy说
"Tammy,no,I'm really sorry that you had to tell me you know.
"不 我很抱歉要你开口我才做
I should have done it without..."
我早该做了"
And she said,"no no no no.This is what I love about you so much.
她说"不 我就是爱你这一点
You are so considerate and you listen to me when I talk."
你如此体贴 肯仔细聆听我"
So I did the dishes too.
于是我又把盘子洗了
Again,benefit creating rather than only benefit finding
创造优点 而非单纯感知优点
or focusing on what doesn't work.
而不是专注于不顺利的地方
I will not see you on Tuesday.
周二就不来给你们上课了
I'm away for,almost the whole week of passover.
我有一整周来不了 过逾越节
But you'll gonna have a treat on Tuesday,
但你们周二还要来上课
an amazing lecture by Shaun on humor.
Shaun带来的关于幽默的精彩演讲
I will see you.
下节课见
[Cheers and laugh]